Andre Polah Papers
Andre Polah Papers
1915-1949
Polah, Andre, 1892-1949.
3 linear ft.
Papers of the American conductor, violinist. Born in The Hague, Holland. Correspondence (1918-1949); musical programs (1918-1949); clippings about Polah, some relating to his tenure as concertmaster and conductor of the Syracuse Symphony Orchestra; and sheet music.
149526
Biographical History
Andre Polah (1892-1949) was a Dutch musician. Born in Holland, he began studying music at age six, at The Hague in his home country. Later he studied at the Royal Conservatory of Music, then at Liege University and finally the Paris Conservatoire. At sixteen he began playing violin in concert. In 1917, at the end of World War I, Polah was released from a German prison camp and came with his Belgian teacher, Eugene Ysaye, to the United States. That year he began touring with John McCormack and later conducted and played in concert with symphony orchestras worldwide. He eventually secured a position as head of the violin department at Syracuse University in the late 1920s, conducting their orchestra as well. In 1935 he was invited to be concertmaster of the Syracuse Symphony Orchestra, a position he held for four years. His music was well received throughout his career.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Andre Polah Papers consists of correspondence, music, and news clippings.
Correspondence contains letters from Arthur Hartmann (Hungarian-born American violinist, composer and friend of Claude Debussy) and Rose O'Neill (illustrator, sculptor, designer, artist, writer), as well as a few miscellaneous items. Music includes both sheet music and material related to musical performances, such as programs and a sketch of a set for Gluck's Orpheus. News clippings contains clippings about Polah, spanning more than thirty years.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is alphabetical by name. Music-related material is alphabetical by type. News clippings are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Hartmann, Arthur, 1881-1956.; O'Neill, Rose Cecil, 1874-1944.; Polah, Andre, 1892-1949.; Syracuse Symphony Orchestra.; Conductors (Music) -- United States.; Dutch Americans.; Music -- 20th century.; Musicians -- United States.; Violinists -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Programs (documents); Sheet music.; Conductors (Music).; Musicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Hartmann, Arthur, 1931-1939; 1949; includes undated photograph of Hartmann (Box 1)
  - O'Neill, Rose, 1925; 1930-1940; includes undated photograph of Hartmann (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Music
  - Blueprint, Gluck's Orpheus, Crouse College, Syracuse University, 1929 (Oversize 1)
  - Programs, Andre Polah, 1918-1949; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Sketch, Gluck's Orpheus, Provincetown Playhouse, 1926 (Oversize 1)
  - Sheet music by Polah
    - Ballet of the Flowers by Henry Hadley, transcriptions for violin and piano by Andre Polah (Box 2)
    - Chaconne from the Fourth Sonate of Joh. Seb. Bach, Transcription for Orchestra (and Chorus lib.) (Oversize 1)
    - Chorale-Prelude ("I Call to Thee, Oh Lord") / Bach-Polah (Oversize 1)
    - Reverie (Oversize 1)
  - Sheet music by others
    - Shawnee Indian Hunting Dance, by Charles Sanford Skilton (Oversize 1)
- News clippings
  - Clippings, 1915-1941 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1941-1949 (Box 3)